Guide to the Christodora House Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Christodora House Records,
1897-1991
Christodora House.
12.5 linear feet in 31 boxes
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY.
5012635
History
Christodora was founded in 1897 as a settlement house on Manhattan's Lower East Side to provide health care, educational and job training programs and other social services to poor immigrant families. Christodora House also served as a home for art and drama clubs. Christodora's Poet's Guild included Robert Frost Vachel Lindsay and Edwin Arlington Robinson and it inspired Ira Gershwin.
Scope and Content
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Adminstration 1897-1990
Series II: Board of Directors 1897-1991
Series III: Clubs 1897-1952
Series IV: Photographs 1900-1985
Series V: Scrapbooks 1897-1961
Subjects
Christodora House.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937.; Social settlements.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Administration
  - Anniversaries, 1947, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Athletics, 1906; 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biele Correspondence, 1932-35 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budget Proposal, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calendar, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Camp Ampersand, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Camper Lists, 1916, nd (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Christmas, 1917, 1941-58 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Christodora,", 1898, 1912-14, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Christodora Hymn,", nd (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Christodora News,", 1934-35, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Christodora Year Book,", 1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - City of Christodora House, 1916-17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1897-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contributions, 1911-24 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Contributions, 1925-30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Contributions, 1927-29, 1933-34 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Contributions, 1927-36 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Contributions, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Corporate Certificates, 1897-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dances, 1931-47 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Drama and Dance Performances, 1906-59, nd (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial Ledger, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Flagship,", 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Flyers and Announcements, 1934-50s, nd (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gershwin, nd (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Guest Register, 1918-39 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Guest Register, 1933-38 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Health Service, 1935-50 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Histories, 1926-80s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reminiscences, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - History-Edward Steiner, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Harry Hopkins, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Information for Members,", 1941-42 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - James Foundation, 1941-49 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - James Foundation, 1950-59 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - James Foundation, 1960-65 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - MacColl Correspondence, 1903-35 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - MacColl Memorial, 1939-40 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - MacColl Reception, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Manice Education Center, 1980s-90s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Membership, 1936-48 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Membership-Boys, 1920-21 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Membership-Boys, 1921-22 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Membership-Girls, 1920-21 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1928-56 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Music Program, 1906-47 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - National Federation of Settlements, 1940-46 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Neighborhood Statistics, 1930, nd (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newsclippings, c., 1898-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Northover Camp, 1908-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Northover Camp-Song Books, nd (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Organization Chart, nd (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Other Organizations, 1936-59 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Press Release, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Program and Event Schedules, 1945-59, nd (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program Reports and Proposals, c. 1930-86, nd (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Promotional Materials, 1906-80s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate-147 Avenue B, 1928-48, 1984-86 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate-84-86 East First Street, 1964-67 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Real Estate-Massachusetts, 1981-85 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Relocation, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Residents, 1930-47 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Staff Manuals, 1932-42 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Struwing Correspondence, 1945, nd (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Thrift Fund, nd (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series II: Board of Directors
  - Annual Reports, 1902-04 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1905-06 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1908-09 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1910-11 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1912, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1916-17 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1918-19 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1920-22 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1923-26 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1927-34 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1941-42 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports, 1948-49 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1950-56 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1957-63 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1964-66 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1966-68 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1968-70 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1970-72 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1972-74 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1974-76 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1976-78 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1980-81 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Members-Elliman, 1964-66 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Members-James, 1909-37 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Members-Lincoln, 1959-68 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Members-Manice, 1961-63 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Members-Manice, Correspondence, 1935-38 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Members-Miscellaneous, 1913, 1946-76 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1897-1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1905-11 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1912-15 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1916-18 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1919-20 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1921-23 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1924-27 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1928-30 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1931-33 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1934-35 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1937-38 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1939-40 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1941-42 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1943-44 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1945-46 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1955-56 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1957-58 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1959-60 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1961-62 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1963-64 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1969-70 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1971-72 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1973-75 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1976-77 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1978-79 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1987-88 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1989-91 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Series III: Clubs
  - Aimwell, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Aimwell, 1918-20 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Aloha, 1908-09 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Aloha, 1909-10 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Aloha, 1915-16 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Alpals, 1922-23 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Alpals, 1922-23 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Alpals, 1923-24 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Bluebird, 1916-17 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Bluebird, 1916-20 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Bluebird, 1917-19 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Boy Scouts, 1924-25, 1951-52 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Button, 1918-21 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Button, 1918-27 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Button, 1919-22 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Button, 1921-24 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Carol, 1926-27 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Clionion, 1898-99 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Clionion, 1898-99 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Clionion, 1910-11 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Club/House Council-Minutes, 1919-27 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Club/House Council-Minutes, 1929-34 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Club/House Council-Minutes, 1935-36 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Debate Notes, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Deoc/Amister, 1923-26 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Girl Scouts, 1944-51 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Hamilton, 1920-21 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Happy Heart, 1911-19 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Happy Heart, 1911-16, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Helping Hand, 1917-30 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Loyalty-Constitution, 1897 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1898 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1899 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1900-01 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1902-03 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1904-14 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1915-17 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, 1925-26 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Loyalty-Correspondence, nd (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1897-98 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1898-1900 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1908-11 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1911-12 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1913-15 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1916-19 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Loyalty-Minutes, 1920-26 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Lucy Larcom, 1902-07 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922-44, nd (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1904-06 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1905-08 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1907-10 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1910-15 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1919-22 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Mother's-Minutes, 1923-24 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Mother's-Miscellaneous, 1903-15, 1944-52 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Mother's-Roll Books, 1903, 1915-24 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Northover Cadets, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Patriotic, 1910-12 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Poet's Guild, 1940-41, nd (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Sangster, 1897-98 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Sangster, 1899-1902 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sangster, 1905-10 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Sangster, 1913-14 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Sangster, 1919-21 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Service, 1917-20 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Spartan, 1919-21 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Spartan, 1921, nd (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Steadfast, 1903-04, nd (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Steadfast, 1910-12 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Sunshine, 1900-05 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Sunshine, 1907-09 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Sunshine, 1909-13 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Tansh Palofa, 1927-28 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Waiting, 1911 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Waverly, 1929-33 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Work and Win, 1907-09, 1912-13 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Work and Win, 1914-18 (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Arts and Crafts, 1950s-60s (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Athletics, c. 1900s-60s (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Board Members, Residents and Staff, c. 1900s-80s (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Building Exterior, c. 1900s-60s (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Building Interior, c.1920s-50s (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Boys Programs, c. 1906-08 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    These photographs were likely taken by the photographer John Howard Toynbee Falk
  - Camp-Building Exterior, c. 1910s-60s (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Camp-Building Interior, c. 1930s-50s (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Camp-Children, c., 1900s-60s (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Camp-Children-Boys, c. 1900s-50s (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Camp-Children-Girls, c. 1900s-50s (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Camp-Landscapes, c. 1910s-50s (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Camp-Miscellaneous, c. 1900s-50s (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Camp-Pool, c. 1940s-60s (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Children, c. 1900s-60s (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Dramatics, c. 1910s-61 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Education, c. 1980s (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Health Care, c. 1910s-50s (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Kiwanis Day Camp, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, c. 1910s-50s (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Mother's Club, c. 1920s-40s (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Music Lessons, c. 1910s-50s (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - National Federation of Settlements, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Scenes, c. 1900s-50s (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Senior Citizens, 1950s-60s (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Teenagers, c. 1910s-50s (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Wood Shop, 1950s (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Negatives-Camp, c. 1900s-60s (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Negatives-Environmental Education, c. 1980s (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Negatives-Miscellaneous, c. 1900s-60s (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Oversize Photographs, c. 1920-60s (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  - 1897-1958 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - 1950s (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - 1960-61 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - 1898-1904 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - 1908-20 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - 1905-18 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - 1920-24 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Northover Camp, 1908-1918 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - 1927-30 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - 1931-34 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - 1936-40 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - 1940-45 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - 1945-55 (Box 31, Folder 1)